A Register of the John K. Cooley papers, 1952-2008
Hoover Institution Archives
John K. Cooley papers
1952-2008
63001
Cooley, John K., 1927-2008
15 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box (6.3 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Papers contain memoirs, other writings, notes, correspondence, memoranda, printed matter, and photographs, relating to the Middle East in international affairs; international terrorism, especially in relation to Libya; the Algerian war for independence; the Organisation Armée secrète; and international counterfeiting. Papers document in part the career of Cooley, an American journalist; Christian Science Monitor Middle East correspondent, 1965-1978; and ABC News Middle East correspondent, 1981-1999.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1963.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Materials
Yves Jean Godard papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Alexander Harrison papers, Hoover Institution Archives
André Figueras sound recordings, Hoover Institution Archives
Alfred M. Lilienthal papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Biographical/Historical Note
1927, November 25 Born, New York City
Graduated, Dartmouth College
1946-1947, 1951-1953 Military and U.S. government service, Vienna
1954 Editorial writer, New York Herald Tribune
1957-1964 Free lance journalist in North Africa
1965 Published Baal, Christ and Muhammed: Religion and Revolution in Africa(New York: Holt Rinehart and Winston)
1965-1978 Middle East staff correspondent, Christian Science Monitor
1966 Published East Wind Over Africa(New York: Walker and Co.)
1973 Published, Green March, Black September: The Story of Palestinian Arabs(London: Frank Cass)
1978-1981 Pentagon correspondent, Christian Science Monitor
1981-1998 Staff correspondent, London and the Middle East, ABC News
1981 Published, Libyan Sandstorm: The Story of Qaddafi's Revolution (New York: New Republic Books)
1992 Published, Payback: America's Long War in the Middle East (Brassey's)
1995 Received George Polk Memorial Career Award for Distinguished Reporting, Long Island University
1999 Published, Unholy Wars: Afghanistan, America, and International Terrorism(London: Pluto Press, updated editions in 2001, 2002)
2002 Published, An Alliance Against Babylon: America, Israel and Iraq
2008 Published,Currency Wars
2008, August 6 Died, Athens, Greece
Scope and Content of Collection
The John K. Cooley papers at the Hoover Institution Archives began as a collection of miscellaneous documents created and acquired by Cooley while reporting as a journalist from Algeria during that country's war for independence in the early 1960s. This material was donated by Cooley to the Hoover Institution Archives in 1963, and includes propaganda leaflets, interview transcripts, transcripts of Cooley's news dispatches and radio broadcasts, and other printed matter, especially material relating to the French military revolt led by the Organisation Armée Secrète in Algiers in 1961.
The remaining papers in this collection were donated by Cooley's family shortly after his death in 2008, and chiefly document his activities as a journalist and author from the 1970s onward, while he worked for the Christian Science Monitor as well as ABC News, based alternately in Lebanon, Cyprus, and Greece. Although Cooley had maintained an extensive personal archive throughout his career as a journalist in North Africa and the Middle East, much of it was lost in 1975, when he was forced to flee his home in Beirut during the Lebanese Civil War.
The papers in his extant collection are divided in series by writings and speeches, research projects for ABC News, photographs, personal papers, and collected miscellany. The writings contain material related to some of his earlier books, but the bulk consists of typescript drafts and background materials for his last two books, An Alliance against Babylon (2005) and Currency Wars(2008). In addition, reprints of published articles and newspaper stories, as well as drafts of stories, texts of speeches and conference papers, and proposed projects are also included. Many of the speeches and unpublished conference papers contain autobiographical material about Cooley and his career as a journalist, and chapter drafts of his unfinished memoirs are also included in this series. A separate series is provided for research material related to stories he was assigned with ABC News. Of note in this series is the research he conducted while working on an Emmy Award-winning ABC News Primetime television special on the bombing of Pan Am Flight 103 over Lockerbie, Scotland in 1988. In addition to his work on the ABC project, Cooley also planned to write a book about the bombing, and material on that can be found in the series on proposed projects. Rounding out the collection are assorted photographs Cooley took or collected while on assignment in Algeria, Yemen, Western Sahara, Morocco, and Lebanon; as well as reporters' notebooks containing notes from interviews and for stories he planned to write.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into 8 series, by format of material and then chronologically within the series and subseries.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Middle East--Foreign relations.; Middle East--Politics and government.; Terrorism.; Counterfeits and counterfeiting.; Organisation Armée secrète.; Algeria--History--Revolution, 1954-1962.; France--History--1958-; Libya--History--1969-; Journalism--United States.; Journalism.
Collection Contents
- Collected Algerian Materials, 1960-1962 (Box 1-2)
  Brochures, press releases, broadcast transcripts, interview transcripts, notes, reports, and memoranda concerning the Algerian war for independence and the coup staged by the Organisation Armée Secrète in 1961. Includes inventory by John K. Cooley of this 1963 accession.
  - Inventory by John K. Cooley (1963 accession) (Folder 1: 1)
  - Algiers military coup, April 19-27, 1961 (Folder 1)
    - Dispatch to Christian Science Monitor, containing background information on the Organisation Armée Secrète, April 18 (Folder 1: 2)
    - Eyewitness account of Challe take-over, cabled to Radio Press International, London, and Christian Science Monitor, but blocked by censorship, April 22 (Folder 1: 3)
    - Scripts of news broadcasts from Cooley to Radio Press International, London, transmitted from "Radio France" (name which insurgents gave to Algiers radio), April 22 (Folder 1: 4)
      Includes changes made at request of Colonel Gardes, who censored outgoing broadcasts
    - Broadcasts from Cooley to CBC, London, on "Radio France,", April 23 (Folder 1: 5)
    - Carbon copy of diplomatic report, concerning Saharan petroleum, gas and other resources being surveyed at that time, due to possibility of extended blockade by the French government forces, April 20 (Folder 1: 6)
    - Notes taken on breakdown of loyalist and insurgent officers, including list of those imprisoned by junta, April 22 (Folder 1: 7)
    - Dispatch to Christian Science Monitor, read on "Radio France,", April 24 (Folder 1: 8)
    - Radio broadcasts to Radio Press International and CBC, concerning the possibility of paratroop landing in France, and statements by Challe and Salan (censored), April 24 (Folder 1: 9)
    - Uncensored dispatch prepared for Christian Science Monitor, intended to be smuggled out but never sent, April 24 (Folder 1: 10)
    - Handwritten memoranda of conversations with two clandestine pro-government officer informants concerning military situation, undated (Folder 1: 11)
    - Thermofax copy of proclamation prepared and broadcast by Challe on "Radio France," concerning activity of army, April 24 (Folder 1: 12)
    - Script of broadcast on "Radio France,", April 25 (Folder 1: 13)
      Includes two alterations made by censor and censor's signature on each page
    - Broadcasts made after return of government control, April 26 (Folder 1: 14)
      Includes account of government takeover, final skirmishes, and forum on night of April 25
    - Broadcasts concerning Foreign Legion refusal to return to government authority, April 27 (Folder 1: 15)
    - Dispatches and broadcasts concerning aftermath of coup, April 28 (Folder 1: 16)
    - Copy of Algiers afternoon newspaper, Dernière Heure, April 23 (Folder 1: 17)
    - Copy of Le Journal d'Alger, April 24 (Folder 1: 18)
    - Copy of La Dépêche: Quotidien de l'Algerie, April 24 (Folder 1: 19)
  - Interviews with Front de Libération Nationale (FLN) leaders in Cairo, 1960 (Folder 1)
    - Abbas, Ferhat (typescript), October 16, 1960 (Folder 1: 20)
    - Beklacem, Krim (typescript), November 25, 1960 (Folder 1: 21)
  - Miscellaneous FLN releases and propaganda (Folder 1-2)
    - Political bulletins of GPRA mission, Rabat, December 8, 1961; January 2 and 19, 1962 (Folder 1: 22)
    - Appeal by Ferhat Abbas to the Algerian people, Tunis, December 16, 1960 (Folder 2: 1)
    - Brochure, Aspects of the Algerian Revolution, undated (Folder 2: 2)
  - Other materials, 1960 (Folder 2)
    - Handouts, titled "Algérie 1960," given to journalists, on miscellaneous aspects of the Algerian question. Produced by French government information services, Algiers (Folder 2: 3)
- Biographical File, 1996-2008 (Box 2)
  Resume, biographical essays, obituaries.
  - Resumes, news articles about John K. Cooley, 1996-2008 (Folder 2: 4)
  - George Polk Award, 1996 (Folder 2: 5)
  - Obituaries, 2008 (Folder 2: 6)
- Writings and Speeches, 1952-2008 (Box 2-9)
  Typescript drafts, printed material, newspaper clippings, and research material related to books, newspaper stories, magazine articles, and speeches written by Cooley, and projects he proposed as well.
  Arranged in sub-series by type of material, and then chronologically.
  - Books (Folder 2-4)
    - Baal, Christ, and Muhammed, 1965 (Folder 2: 7)
      - Publicity, 1965 (Folder 2: 7)
    - Libyan Sandstorm: The Complete Account of Qaddafi's Revolution, 1982 (Folder 2: 8)
      - Reviews, 1982-1983 (Folder 2: 8)
    - Payback: America's Long War in the Middle East, 1991 (Folder 2: 9)
      - Reviews, 1991-1992 (Folder 2: 9)
    - Unholy Wars: Afghanistan, America, and International Terrorism, 1999 (Folder 2: 9)
      - Reviews and publicity, 2000-2002 (Folder 2: 10)
      - Packet of Italian articles (sent by publisher) reviewing Unholy Wars in Italy, 2001-2006 (Folder 2: 11)
    - An Alliance Against Babylon: America, Israel and Iraq, 2005 (Folder 2)
      - Revised manuscript and author's letter to Pluto highlighting the book's contributions and highlights, 2003 (Folder 2: 12)
      - Earlier draft, 2003 (Folder 2: 13-14)
      - Research materials (Folder 2-3)
        - Main binder (with author's annotations indicating future chapters) (Folder 2: 15)
        - Main binder (with author's annotations indicating future chapters) (contd.) (Folder 3: 1)
        - Secondary binder (Folder 3: 2)
      - Proposed covers (Folder 3: 3)
    - Currency Wars, 2008 (Folder 3)
      - Blue notebook. Handwritten draft of Chapter 13 of Currency wars (Folder 3: 4)
      - "Supernotes: The Counterfeiters' Secret War against America." Book Proposal and Outline, Version 1, 1997 (Folder 3: 5)
      - "Supernotes: The Secret War of Counterfeiters against America," Version 2, 1997 (Folder 3: 6)
      - "Funny Money: The Counterfeiters in History and the New Europe," summary outline with hand-written notes, Draft Chapter 1, 2001 (Folder 3: 7)
      - "Funny Money: Counterfeiters & Money Launderers- Their Threat in History and the Age of New Terrorism," revised summary outline, 2001 (Folder 3: 8)
      - "Money Power: Counterfeiting as Crime and Weapon of War." Book proposal, outline and draft chapter 2, 2005 (Folder 3: 9)
      - "Currency Wars," first draft with corrections, 2007 (2 folders) (Folder 3: 10-11)
      - Research material (Folder 3)
        - General (Folder 3: 12)
        - General (contd.) (Folder 4: 1)
        - Counterfeiting in the United States (Folder 4: 2)
        - Counterfeiting in Europe (Folder 4: 3)
        - Early research (Crane Paper Company), 1996-1997 (2 folders) (Folder 4: 4-5)
        - Operation Bernhard (German counterfeiting ring in World War II) (Folder 4: 6)
  - Newspaper articles, 1952-2008 (Folder 4-5)
    - New York Herald articles, clippings, 1952-1953 (Folder 4: 7)
    - Christian Science Monitor, 1957-1980 (Folder 4)
      - 1957-1961 (Folder 4: 8)
      - 1975 Oversize (Folder 16)
      - 1976 Oversize (Folder 16)
      - 1977 Oversize (Folder 16)
      - Pentagon stories, 1978-1981 (Folder 5: 1)
      - 1978 (Folder 5: 2)
      - 1979 (Folder 5: 3)
      - 1980 (Folder 5: 4)
    - Articles in various publications, clippings and photocopies, 1980-2008 (Folder 5)
      - 1980-1989 (Folder 5: 5)
      - 1990-1999 (Folder 5: 6)
      - 2000-2008 (Folder 5: 7)
    - ABC News website commentaries, 1996-2003 (Folder 5: 8)
  - Magazine articles and book chapters, 1996-2003 (Folder 6)
    - "Cross and Crescent,"The Commonweal, November 24, 1961 (Folder 6: 1)
    - "King Hassan's Unbound Morocco," The Reporter, October 11, 1962 (Folder 6: 2)
    - "Conflict within the Iraqi Left,"Problems of Post-Communism, January-February 1980 (Folder 6: 3)
    - "The News from the Mideast: A Working Approach,"Middle East Journal, Autumn 1981 (Folder 6: 4)
    - The War over Water,Foreign Policy, Spring 1984 (Folder 6: 5)
    - "Libya," prepared for Handbook of the Arab World, 1986 (Folder 6: 6)
    - "Pre-Gulf War Diplomacy," Survival, March/April, 1991 (Folder 6: 7)
    - "Death of a Diplomat: John K. Cooley's Memories of 1974," published in 50 Years: Cyprus Mail, (Nicosia, 1995) (Folder 6: 8)
    - "Middle Eastern Terrorism: The Palestinian-Israeli Conflict," written for the Encyclopedia of Terrorism (published by M.E. Sharpe), 1996 (Folder 6: 9)
    - "Vienna 1946," original draft in English, September 2002, and published version (in Italian) Diario Milano, January 2003 (Folder 6: 10)
    - "Proxies and Proxy Wars: 20th Century Mishaps and Disasters," prepared for Rethink: Causes and Consequences of September 11, edited by Giorgio Baravalle, 2004 (Folder 6: 11)
  - Draft articles and works in progress, 1950s-2008 (Folder 6)
    - Bin Laden's Shadow Spotted in the Balkans, undated, circa 2001 (Folder 6: 12)
    - The Dream of Samarra: Saints and Sorcerers in the Western Sahara, undated, circa 1950s (Folder 6: 13)
    - Epilogue: The Globalization of Violence, date unknown (Folder 6: 14)
    - "From the Red Army to the Zaibatsu" (Japanese leftist connection to Palestinians), draft chapter, date unknown (Folder 6: 15)
    - "The Genteel Sovereign: A Reminiscence of King Hussein ibn Talal of Jordan", date and venue unknown (Folder 6: 16)
    - "Iran, Maghreb and Afghanistan: Landmarks" Autobiographical sketch, date and venue unknown (Folder 6: 17)
    - Israel and Iraq: Convoluted Antagonism, date and venue unknown (Folder 6: 18)
    - "Israel and the Iraq Wars" Outline for an article based on book Alliance with Babylon (Folder 6: 19)
    - Remembrances of Saleh Taamri, date and venue unknown (Folder 6: 20)
    - Terrorism: Continuity and Change in the 20th Century, undated, circa 2000 (Folder 6: 21)
    - "Who Cares About Syria?" Draft article originally prepared for submission to the Washington Quarterly, not published, circa 1984 (Folder 6: 22)
    - Who's Afraid of Militant Islam?, undated (Folder 6: 23)
    - "A War against Saddam Is No Local Conflict," written for the International Herald Tribune, December 14, 1990 (Folder 6: 24)
    - "Greece Wants to Stop Changing Balkan Frontiers," written for the International Herald Tribune, July 25, 1992 (Folder 6: 25)
    - "In the Mideast and Balkans, the Russians Try Hard for a Comeback," written for the International Herald Tribune, May 2, 1994 (Folder 6: 26)
    - "Beirut Blues, by Hanan al-Shakykh" (book review), written for the International Herald Tribune, May 8, 1995 (Folder 6: 27)
    - "After Oslo: New Realities, Old Problems" (book review), written for the Journal of Palestinian Studies, 1998 (Folder 6: 28)
    - Who Really Dunnit? We May Never Know: a Comment for Perspective on 10th Anniversary of Pan-Am 103 Bombing, 1998 (Folder 6: 29)
    - "The Palestinians Need Hanan Ashrawi's Brainy Leadership?" written for the International Herald Tribune, May 29, 2002 (Folder 6: 30)
    - "September 11 Anniversary: History Lessons," prepared for Diario, August 2002, publication date unknown (Folder 6: 31)
    - Wanted: Urgent Action to Mid-East Water Issues, September 23, 2002 (Folder 6: 32)
    - "The War that Spared New York" (German World War II plans to bomb New York), written for the International Herald Tribune, 2003 (Folder 6: 33)
    - "Homeless in Gaza," written for Diario Magazine, May 18, 2004 (Folder 6: 34)
    - "U.S. Homeland Security and the Atlantic U-boat War, 1942-44," Written in 2005 for the US Naval Institute's Essay Contest on Naval Intelligence (Folder 6: 35)
    - "Friendship and Professionalism in the Old Beirut," draft of tribute to Peter Jennings, written for the Christian Science Monitor, August 2005 (Folder 6: 36)
    - "Iran, Iraq and the Gulf: The Fire Again?" draft prepared for the Harvard International Review, March 2006, published in Summer 2006 (Folder 6: 37)
    - "Can Putin Fight Russia's Money Forgery Problem?" 2007, draft for International Herald Tribune (Folder 6: 38)
    - Oil and Cyprus, February 2007 (Folder 6: 39)
    - "Currency Counterfeiting," written for Esquire magazine, (December 2007) (Folder 6: 40)
    - Counterfeiting article submitted to Foreign Policy, May 2008 (Folder 6: 41)
  - Proposed projects, 1954-2008 (Folder 7-8)
    - Land of the Nearest East, unpublished book manuscript, undated, circa 1954 (Folder 7: 1)
    - Mohammed Khidder book (Folder 7)
      - Background material, 1979-1980 (Folder 7: 2)
      - Book outline, undated (Folder 7: 3)
      - Chapter drafts, undated (Folder 7: 4)
      - Signed declaration of widow of Khidder, 1979 (Folder 7: 5)
    - World War II espionage novel: notes and background material, circa 1990s (Folder 7: 6)
    - Tibet reportage, 1995 (story proposal for the Washington Post, draft articles for The Guardian, Cyprus Mail and International Herald Tribune, suggested storyboard outline for ABC News feature, and background material) (Folder 7: 7)
    - Libya: International Crisis Group report (proposed), 2002-2003 (4 folders) (Folder 7: 8-10)
    - Libya: International Crisis Group report (proposed), 2002-2003 (contd.) (Folder 8: 1)
    - "Pan Am 103 or Delayed Justice," book proposal (with Wilhelm Dietl) (Folder 8)
      - Book proposal summary and chapter outline (Folder 8: 2)
      - Authors' correspondence (Folder 8: 3)
      - Background papers and materials, 2002-2008 (Folder 8: 4-6)
    - Personal memoirs (incomplete), undated, circa 2007-2008 (Folder 8)
      - Background material (including U.S. Army Corps of Engineers proposal on Franco-American air base in Morocco) (Folder 8: 7)
      - Chapter drafts and notes (Folder 8: 8)
  - Speeches and conference papers, 1991-2005 (Folder 9-10)
    - "Covering the Kuwait Crisis, 1990-1991," Conference on the Media and the Gulf War, Turkish Foreign Press Association, Istanbul, June 7-8, 1991 (Folder 9: 1)
    - "Cleaning Up Middle East Water," prepared for Middle East Economic Summit, November 14, 1996 (Folder 9: 2)
    - Censorship, Technology and Foreign Reporting, 1997 (Folder 9: 3)
    - "The Frankenstein Syndrome: Unforeseen Consequences of the CIA's Jihad in Afghanistan, 1979-1989," Conference of SHAFR, Georgetown University, June 19, 2002, 1997 (Folder 9: 4)
    - "Images and Realities in the Palestinian World," Center for Policy Analysis on Palestine. Washington DC, September 11, 1998 (Folder 9: 5)
    - CUNY Conference on Globalization and the Media, 1999 (Folder 9: 6)
    - "Consequences of the 1979-89 Jihad," note for possible presentation, February 17, 2000 (Folder 9: 7)
    - "War and the Druglords in South Asia," prepared for delivery at the HNN conference on Drugs, Visby, Sweden, May 3-6, 2001 (Folder 9: 8)
    - "Libyan History, Libyan Legends," prepared for delivery at conference on Libya's future, Washington DC, October 2001 (Folder 9: 9)
    - "The 'Anti-Terror' War since Sept. 11," prepared for delivery at La Maison de l'Europe, Paris, March 5, 2002 (Folder 9: 10)
    - "Old Roots of 'New' Terrorism," prepared for delivery at the CCAS, Georgetown University, March 27, 2003 (Folder 9: 11)
    - "Arab Development: Sequels are Needed," presented at the UNDP-AHDR conference, Ifrane, Morocco, December 11-14, 2003 (Folder 9: 12)
    - "Privatizing War and Occupation," prepared for Launch of Rethink 9/11, Tufts University, February 25, 2004 (Folder 9: 13)
    - "Terrorism: Constants and Verities," Prepared for the EPIIC Forum, Tufts University, February 29, 2004 (Folder 9: 14)
    - "The United States in the Middle East: A Half Century of Change," prepared for delivery at the University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, Michigan, March 9, 2005 (Folder 9: 15)
    - "Failures of Intelligence? Or Un-Intelligent Failures," prepared for delivery at the US Congressional Black Caucus Hearing on 9/11 Commission Report Omissions, Washington DC, September 23-25, 2005 (Folder 9: 16)
    - The Making of a Foreign Correspondent (Folder 9: 17)
- Subject Files/ABC News, 1982-2002 (Box 9-11)
  Typescript drafts, printed material, newspaper and magazine clippings, and videocassette, related to research Cooley conducted for reports he contributed to on ABC News.
  - Counterfeiting (Supernotes), 1996-1997 (Folder 9: 18-19)
  - Crypto AG (Zurich), 1994 (Folder 9: 20)
  - Iraqi antiquities, theft of, 1999 (Folder 10: 1)
  - John Paul II, Pope; Assassination attempt, 2000-2002 (Folder 10)
    - Memos, ABC News research, background and correspondence (Folder 10: 2)
    - Transcript of ABC News interview, Peter Jennings with Father Jean Calvez (Folder 10: 3)
    - Background material (Folder 10: 4-5)
  - Pan-Am 103 / Lockerbie bombing, 1989-2000 (Folder 10-11)
    - Background material and correspondence, 1989-1991 (Folder 10: 6)
    - Background material and correspondence, 1999-2000 (Folder 10: 7)
    - Transcript of Primetime television special, 1989 (Folder 10: 8)
    - Videotape of Primetime television special, 1989 (Folder 11: 1)
  - Philadelphia Experiment (regarding attempt to make a U.S. naval ship invisible to detection), 1997 (Folder 11: 2)
  - Various investigative stories, ABC News, 1998-2000 (Folder 11: 3)
  - Water management conflict in the Middle East, 1982-1983 (Folder 11: 4)
- Photographs, 1958-1990 (Box 11-12)
  Photographic prints and negatives, both created by and collected by Cooley, arranged by topic.
  - Photographs collected by John Cooley, 1958-1990 (Folder 11)
    - Ayatollah Morteza Pasindideh with Imam, undated (Folder 11: 5)
    - Prince Reza Pahlavi, single portrait and visit with California Governor George Deukmejian, undated and 1990 (2 prints) (Folder 11: 6)